Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
So today's דף daf is כ"ה, Chaf-Heh, and we pick up on
the bottom of כ"ד עמוד ב' Chaf-Dalet Amud-Bet
where it is אמר רב זירא אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav
Zeira Af Anan Nami Tanina. So it's really about two-fifths from the
bottom, the line starts with the word נמי תנינא. Nami Tanina. It's
about maybe 20 lines from the bottom.
And after having spent three days discussing
what
constitutes, where we learn out the idea that certain things are forbidden
in הנאה, hana'ah, or to remind us we have חזקיה Chizkiyahu that
learns it out from לא יאכל, Lo Yeachal, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
learns it out from לא יאכל, Lo Yochal, both of them rooted
in the word אכילה. achilah. And the last approach which learns it
out from the idea of קודש kodesh and burning קודש, kodesh, which
is a very different concept, basically a sense of like not associated
with the eating but something that's completely off-limits and taboo. Now we
turn to practical implications or practical parameters of things that are אסור
בהנאה. asur behana'ah. And the first statement we had was that of
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
which makes sense that it is again רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu because
again this is we'll see in a minute connected to the idea
of אכילה achilah that number one things that you're not allowed to
eat you're only חייב chayav if you eat them in a normal
way and normal meaning in the normal way of sort of deriving
pleasure through the act of eating. So for example eating raw fat
you would not transgress. That makes a certain degree of sense, there's
parameters that define what constitutes an act of eating. But then you
had another a more radical version of that statement which is even
if you derive benefit for things that are forbidden in benefit, it
has to be a normal way of deriving benefit. So if you
put the fat of a שור הנסקל shor niskal on a wound
to heal the wound, you don't transgress. Even though the benefit was
a normal benefit, it's normal to, you know, healing a wound is
a normal benefit. So you might think that there's no process defined
as a process of deriving benefit. The end result is you got
benefit from this fat. No, we say that the process has to
be a normal way of going about it and that's not a
normal way of using this fat. And that presumably is because,
and the גמרא Gemara will be explicit about this in a minute,
that it's linked to the idea of eating, so the same way
there's a process for eating, there's also a process for deriving benefit,
especially if we learn this idea of deriving benefit from this idea
of eating. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues with this.
אמר רבי זירא אף אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Rabbi Zeira Af Anan
Nami Tanina, we taught similarly to this approach. אין סופגין את הארבעים
משום ערלה אלא על היוצא מן הזיתים ומן הענבים בלבד. Ein Sokim
Arba'im Mishum Orlah Ela Hayotzei Min Hazeitim Umin Ha'anavim Bilvad. The only
time you would get lashes for ערלה Orlah if you drink certain
juices from fruits is fruits that juices that come from olives and
grapes. But if you have let's say orange juice or apple juice,
then that would not be you would not transgress for eating from
the fruit of ערלה Orlah or as we know you can't even
get הנאה hana'ah from ערלה. Orlah. So presumably that you wouldn't even
transgress for getting benefit from ערלה. Orlah. ואילו מתותים תאנים ורמונים, Ve'ilu
Mi'tutim Te'einim Verimonim, so the implication being that if it were some
if you were benefiting from juices of strawberries or or figs or
pomegranates, pomegranates juice, לא, Lo, you would not transgress. מאי טעמא? Mai
Ta'ama? What's the reason? לאו משום דלא קאכיל להו דרך הנאתו? Lav
Mishum Delo Ke'achel Lehu Derech Hana'aso? It must be, now here we're
assuming you're talking about eating not deriving benefit although ערלה Orlah is
also forbidden in benefit, but at least as a support of the
first position that says that by eating it has to be דרך
הנאה, derech hana'ah, this is not a normal way that people derive
pleasure from a pomegranate is not by drinking the juices. All right.
So this is exactly. So this is at a time when the
only recognized sort of liquids, you know, fruit juices, were olive oil
and and wine. So everything else was not considered a normal way
of deriving benefit from the from the fruit. So you see that
at least for eating maybe talking here about eating and not הנאה
hana'ah but at least for eating that's a that is a parameter.
So the so that's a good proof, is it not?
אמר ליה אביי, Amar Lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, No,
that's not necessarily a good proof. בשלמא אשמעינן פרי גופיה דלא קאכיל
ליה דרך הנאתו, Bishlama Ishmanan Pri Gufe Delo Ke'achal Lehu Derech Hana'aso,
if you had talked to me about the fruit itself, the pomegranate
itself, that somehow you ate it in a way that you did
not get normal types of pleasure from it, שפיר, shapir, that would
have been a good proof that the act of eating, it's not
enough to actually chew it and swallow it, there has to be
a normal type of benefit that comes with it. That would have
proved your point. אלא הכא, Ela Hacha, here the reason you're exempt
is not because there's a problem with the process, the process wasn't
a normal way of getting benefit in the act. אלא, Ela, the
reason here you're exempt is מטעמא דזיעה בעלמא הוא, mita'ama demizeia be'alma
hu, that it's only considered like sweat, meaning what? Meaning the problem
wasn't in the act, the problem was in the object. That it
could be, and this is actually, you know, correct the case in
many areas exactly about this. הלכה Halacha does not recognize the status
of fruit juices that are not olive oil and grape juice and
wine. It basically does not see them as. as, you know, as
a real product of the fruit.
So therefore, for example, let's say I give you an example like
the גמרא Gemara often talks about when you squeeze olives, you know,
before the olive oil comes off, there's like some very watery substance
that comes off of an olive that's not yet really the juice
of the olive, it's not yet olive oil. Okay, called מוהל, mohal,
you know? So it says, so would you transgress there for eating
from an olive? So no, that's just some, you know, runoff of
the olive. It's not really considered to represent and be a part
of the fruit itself. You see this, for example, in cases where
it's not about הנאה. hana'ah. When you squeeze, if you were to,
on שבת, Shabbos, you do a מלאכה melacha by squeezing fruit and
extracting their juices. You only biblically transgress when you squeeze olive and
grapes. If you squeeze an orange and get out the juice or
lemon and get out the juice, that is not actually biblical transgression
because what you took out is not considered anything of significance, anything
of real substance. It's just, it's junk. So, you know, weird people
will eat it, but it's junk. But there the problem therefore is
not that you didn't, you ate the forbidden object in a way
that you did not derive benefit. The problem there is that the
object that you extracted is not really considered to be, to be
like the fruit itself. It's considered to be some, some runoff.
Now, if you drank the
whole thing and you slipped it in now, then, alright, so that's
an interesting question, meaning why is it considered to be an extraction
of the fruit and not the fruit in a different form? You
know, and that you might have, you know, that's a good question.
תוספות Tosafot actually ups the question one more. תוספות Tosafot says, and
whatever happened about to the principle about טעם כעיקר? taam ke'ikar? Right?
If I like cook חזיר chazir with an, with a potato, and
the potato has taste of חזיר, chazir, it's אסור. assur. So why
when I squeeze out my orange and now I have liquid that
has orange taste in it, why isn't that at least טעם taam
of the orange? And that actually is a very good question to
which תוספות Tosafot doesn't have a good answer to. Now, it could
be that it is טעם כעיקר, taam ke'ikar, but it's not the
same prohibition. It could be the prohibition of טעם כעיקר taam ke'ikar
is of a lesser nature than the actual thing itself. If you
eat the taste of חזיר, chazir, could be you're not עובר, over,
you don't transgress the prohibition of חזיר, chazir, could be it's a
secondary prohibition. But anyway, this becomes very relevant in the whole issue,
for example, about, about liquor on פסח. Pesach. There are some, you
know, the positions in the אחרונים acharonim about how forbidden is grain
alcohol on פסח. Pesach. Some say that it's like, it's חמץ גמור.
chametz gamur. It comes from grain and water and it's complete חמץ
chametz and it's טעם חמץ taam chametz and the whole thing, basically
focusing on טעם כעיקר. taam ke'ikar. And others say, based on a
גמרא Gemara like this, that it's like זיעה בעלמא, zei'ah be'alma, it's
completely כשר לפסח. kosher l'Pesach. It has no significance at all because
it's not olive oil and it's not, and it's not grape juice.
So anyway, that is a real question, this concept of זיעה בעלמא
zei'ah be'alma and how that's in conversation with other, with another major
concept of טעם כעיקר. taam ke'ikar.
Why would you make מזונות mezonot on bread made with apple juice?
You should make המוציא hamotzi according to that.
Why?
You make the ברכה beracha on it because you never made dough
from it because it's not...
well, that might be, but that's a different issue. That's whether we
consider something to be bread when it's not made with water.
So here you're saying that this is, meaning this is being treated
less than water also.
Well, the זיעה בעלמא zei'ah be'alma is not to say that it
doesn't have the status of water. זיעה בעלמא zei'ah be'alma is to
say that it doesn't have the status of the fruit, of the
fruit.
The issue about what can make, what creates חמץ chametz and what
leavens and what makes לחם, lechem, that's a different discussion. So we'll
get to that. Anyway, the basic answer of the גמרא Gemara is,
I just wanted to signal that that's a real issue here about
how you look at juice, you know, fruit juices, but the basic
answer of the גמרא Gemara is that this might be related to
the object. The object isn't considered the fruit. It might not tell
you something about a process of deriving benefit, whether that's necessary in
the act of eating. Yes, Rebecca.
You can't drink them on a fast, right? Right.
So, but again, זיעה בעלמא zei'ah be'alma is not to say it's
not food. זיעה בעלמא zei'ah be'alma is just to say it's not
the fruit. Okay, it's not significant enough to be considered like the
fruit.
And you don't get מלקות malkos for eating ערלה orlah because you
didn't eat the fruit of the tree. That's the emphasis of the
גמרא. Gemara.
I think it was even even a חלב...
chelev... okay, so anyway, let's go on. So that's the גמרא's Gemara
point here, the difference here is in terms of the object. So
now the גמרא Gemara goes on and says the following:
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So that's in terms of generally you need
דרך הנאה derech hana'ah for eating and maybe you even need דרך
הנאה derech hana'ah for deriving benefit, which is even a bigger חידוש.
chiddush. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, הכל מודין בכלאי הכרם
hakol modin b'kilai hakerem שלוקין עליהן אפילו שלא כדרך הנאתן. she'lokin aleihen
afilu she'lo k'derech hana'atan.
Everybody agrees that when it comes to כלאיים, kilayim, that you get,
right, you're not allowed to derive benefit from כלאיים, kilayim, from two
different, from like grain and vegetable or whatever other seed that was
planted together or grain and grapes that were planted together. Everybody agrees
that you would get lashes, not only is it forbidden and you
transgress, but you get lashes even if you derive benefit in a
non-normal way. Why is that? מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
משום דלא כתיב בהו אכילה mishum d'lo ktiv behu achilah because it
doesn't say you shall not eat כלאיים, kilayim, what does it say
by כלאיים? kilayim? It says לא תזרע... lo tizra... lest the growth
become sanctified.
Notice again the word קודש Kodesh and sanctified and linking into that
model we emphasized yesterday. So the way you know that כלאים Kilayim
is off-limits is not the model of אכילה Achilah and an extension
of אכילה, Achilah, it’s the model of הקדש, Hekdesh, something completely taboo
and off-limits. And here the גמרא Gemara says is where it makes
a difference. If conceptually it’s linked to the idea of eating, then
you would say eating is a process and it has certain parameters
that define it. For example, we’re about to come up to a
fast day or let’s say it was יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, if
you had an IV you would not transgress. If you have an
IV piping חלב Cheilev straight into your system, you would not transgress
eating. Okay? Eating is defined by a certain type of a process
and parameters, one of them is a normal way of benefiting from
the act. So therefore when you can’t derive benefit, if conceptually it’s
rooted in the world of eating, there’s also normal parameters to what
constitutes a normal act of deriving benefit, normal ways of deriving benefit.
But when it’s not rooted in the אכילה Achilah world, when it’s
rooted in the world that we spoke about yesterday, the הקדש Hekdesh
world, כלאים Kilayim is פן תקדש, pen tikdash, it’s completely off-limits and
taboo. Therefore any type of benefit that you get, you’ve transgressed that
taboo as it were, you’ve transgressed that sense of completely off-limits, and
therefore you would transgress regardless of whether it was the normal way
or the not normal way. And he says that would be true
about כלאים Kilayim where the תורה Torah does not use the word
אכילה Achilah but uses the word of הקדש. Hekdesh. Okay, so that
now let’s test that assertion. מאי טעמא? משום דלא כתיבו אכילה. Mai
ta’ama? Mishum delo ketivu achilah. It does not have the phrase of
אכילה. Achilah. מיתיבי: איסי בן יהודה אומר מנין לבשר בחלב שהוא אסור?
Meitivi: Issi ben Yehuda omer minayin levasar bechalav shehu assur? Where do
I know,
from where do I know that בשר בחלב Basar bechalav is forbidden
to eat? Because the תורה Torah only tells me it’s forbidden to
cook. Where do I know it’s forbidden to eat? נאמר כאן: כי
עם קדוש אתה לה' אלוהיך לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו, Ne’emar kan:
Ki am kadosh atah l’Hashem Elokecha lo tevashel gedi bachalev imo,
so the prohibition of בשר בחלב Basar bechalav is introduced with the
idea that you’re a holy nation. ונאמר להלן: ואנשי קדש תהיון לי,
V’ne’emar lehalan: V’anshei kodesh tihyun li, and you shall be a holy
people to me. מה להלן בטריפה, ב'ואנשי קדש תהיון לי ובשר בשדה
טריפה לא תאכלו', Mah lehalan betreifah, b’V’anshei kodesh tihyun li uvasar basadeh
treifah lo tocheilu,
correct, it’s by a טריפה. Treifah. מה להלן אסור, Mah lehalan assur,
the same way there being holy and then introducing some food thing
means you’re holy and therefore separate yourself away from eating this food,
אף כאן אסור, af kan assur, here too by בשר בחלב Basar
bechalav be holy and don’t eat it. ואין לי אלא באכילה. V’ein
li ela ba’achilah. Now that only tells me that you can’t eat
בשר בחלב. Basar bechalav. בהנאה מנין? Bahana’ah minayin? How do I know
you cannot derive benefit from בשר בחלב? Basar bechalav? אמרת: קל וחומר,
Amarta: Kal vachomer,
you can make a קל וחומר. Kal vachomer. Now everybody here who’s
learned חומש Chumash with רש"י Rashi will say: what do you mean?
Because it says it three times! One tells you you can’t eat
and one tells you you can’t derive benefit. Fine, that’s what רש"י
Rashi says, that’s one opinion in the תנאים. Tannaim. But there are
many, many different opinions in the תנאים Tannaim about how do you
learn that בשר בחלב Basar bechalav can’t be eaten and you can’t
derive benefit since the only thing the תורה Torah says is don’t
cook them together. So this approach says you learn that you can’t
eat it because of the אנשי קודש Anshei Kodesh and the linking
to טריפה Treifah and not eating. How do you know you can’t
derive benefit? קל וחומר, Kal vachomer, you can make it a קל
וחומר. Kal vachomer. ומה ערלה שלא נעבדה בה עבירה אסורה בהנאה, U’mah
orlah shelo ne’evdah bah aveirah asurah bahana’ah, ערלה Orlah
you didn’t do a sin, it’s just the first three years and
nevertheless you can’t derive benefit. בשר בחלב שנעבדה בו עבירה, Basar bechalav
she’ne’evdah bo aveirah, בשר בחלב Basar bechalav which was cooked together, the
only way you get a biblical בשר בחלב Basar bechalav food is
by transgressing, by cooking meat and milk together, I already have done
a transgression. אינו דין שיאסר בהנאה? Eino din sheye’aser bahana’ah? Much more
so should it be אסור Assur in הנאה. Hana’ah. מה לערלה, Mah
l’orlah, so that’s a קל וחומר. Kal vachomer. So the גמרא Gemara
says, nope, maybe not. מה לערלה, Mah l’orlah, דף כ"ה עמוד א',
Daf kaf-hei amud alef, what’s the case by ערלה? Orlah? שכן לא
הייתה לו שעת הכושר, Sheken lo haytah lo sha’at hachosher, ערלה Orlah
never, the food was never kosher to begin with. As soon as
the fruit grew, it was forbidden. By בשר בחלב, Basar bechalav, right,
the meat starts off מותר muttar and the milk starts off מותר.
muttar. So maybe therefore it retains some of its original status and
because it started off מותר muttar maybe it does not become as
forbidden. תאמר בבשר בחלב שהייתה לו שעת הכושר, Tomar bevasar bechalav shehaytah
lo sha’at hachosher, בשר בחלב Basar bechalav had a time when it
was kosher and therefore maybe it remains at least permissible in benefit.
This is בשר בחלב Basar bechalav is not kosher stuff, then right?
Because it’s not kosher. Yeah, but but you don’t have that. I
mean, whatever, but anyway at least yes. חמץ בפסח יוכיח. Chametz bePesach
yochiach. Oh
no, I’ll give you a counterproof, something that starts off מותר muttar
and in the end it becomes forbidden and even forbidden in benefit.
What is it? חמץ בפסח. Chametz bePesach. Now you’ll remember I should
mention to you so far we’ve mentioned, just so you keep score,
four things that are אסור בהנאה: assur bahana’ah: בשר... basar,
so far we’ve mentioned חמץ בפסח, chametz b'pesach, שור הנסקל, Shor haniskal,
ערלה, Orlah, and כלאים. Kilayim. Okay, we just introduced כלאים Kilayim and
now we’re mentioning בשר בחלב, Basar bechalav, just so you keep in
mind the things we’ve mentioned that are אסור בהנאה. assur bahana’ah. So
first we’re trying to prove it from ערלה, Orlah, that doesn’t do
the job.
Let’s try... So the same thing should be true by בשר בחלב,
basar bechalav, which is even worse because you did an עבירה aveirah
with בשר
בחלב. basar bechalav. מה לחמץ בפסח שכן ענוש כרת. mah l'chametz b'pesach
she'ken onush kares. That's more severe. If you eat חמץ chametz, בפסח,
you get כרת. kares. So you can't necessarily prove it by בשר
בחלב basar bechalav where you don't get כרת. kares. תאמר בבשר בחלב
שאינו ענוש כרת. tomar b'basar bechalav she'eino onush kares. So now you
can't prove it from ערלה orlah because that never was מותר. mutar.
You can't prove it from חמץ, that's more strict because it had
כרת. kares. So let's try our third thing that we know is
אסור בהנאה. assur behana. כלאי הכרם יוכיח. kilay hakerem yochiach. How about
כלאים kilayim from the vineyard? It mentions specifically of the vineyard because
only כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem of the vineyard is אסור בהנאה. assur
behana. כלאים kilayim of other grains is not אסור בהנאה. assur behana.
כלאי הכרם יוכיח שאין ענוש כרת. kilay hakerem yochiach she'ein onush kares.
They're not, it's not punished by כרת kares ואסור בהנאה. v'assur behana.
And that's also comparable to בשר בחלב basar bechalav because you did
an עבירה. aveirah. You grew כלאים. kilayim.
Okay, so that's the end of that discussion about how we're going
to prove that בשר בחלב basar bechalav is אסור בהנאה assur behana
by comparison or קל וחומר kal vachomer to כלאים. kilayim. Now the
גמרא gemara says, now the reason we're bringing this in is because
of the assertion that כלאים kilayim you transgress even when you get
benefit in the not normal way. So here's the challenge to that
assertion: ואי איתא, v'ee isah, if what you said was correct, that
you transgress כלאים kilayim even with not normal way of benefiting, so
what type of a proof can you bring from כלאים kilayim to
בשר בחלב? basar bechalav?
נפרך, nifroch, why don't we challenge that analogy by saying מה לכלאי
הכרם שכן לוקה עליהן אפילו שלא כדרך הנאתן? mah l'kilay hakerem she'ken
lokeh aleihen afilu shelo k'derech hana'asan? That כלאים kilayim is more severe.
The reason כלאים kilayim is אסור בהנאה assur behana is because it's
so severe even if you eat it and get benefit in the
not normal way. So maybe it's not relevant to בשר בחלב. basar
bechalav. Maybe it's more severe. So obviously that shows that כלאים kilayim
is not severe. Your assertion is wrong. So אביי Abaye answers back:
What type of question is that? ואביי, v'Abaye, אביי Abaye would say
back, תאמר במה, tomar bemah, meaning you want to say כלאים kilayim
is more severe because even not normal benefit is a problem. So
therefore you can't apply it. You can't apply it to what? תאמר
בבשר בחלב שאין לוקה עליו אלא דרך הנאה? tomar b'basar bechalav she'ein
lokeh alav ela derech hana'ah? Meaning the end of that challenge would
be: maybe that's only by כלאים kilayim that it's severe because it's
not normal benefit, and you can't say that by בשר בחלב basar
bechalav where it would only be normal benefit. So he said: Why
not?
אטו בבשר בחלב אכילה כתיבא ביה? atu b'basar bechalav achilah kesivah bei?
He says, I would say the same thing by בשר בחלב. basar
bechalav. Right? By בשר בחלב basar bechalav it doesn't say don't eat
בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. The whole point is it doesn't tell you
not to eat it. It tells you don't cook it. We infer
from learning it out from נבלה neveilah or from other ways we
infer you can't eat בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. So אביי Abaye says
guess what? I'd say the same thing by בשר בחלב. basar bechalav.
I would say by בשר בחלב basar bechalav if you eat בשר
בחלב basar bechalav in a not normal way you also transgress. Okay?
Just like כלאים. kilayim. And by the way I should say that
is the הלכה. halacha. The הלכה halacha is that both by כלאים
kilayim and by בשר בחלב basar bechalav you transgress even if it
is שלא כדרך הנאה. shelo k'derech hana'ah. And this actually has very
important relevance. Because let's say for
example you actually cooked something that was בשר בחלב basar bechalav and
then I don't know it got charred or disgusting or something like
that and you went ahead and you ate it anyway. So at
a certain point it might stop being considered food, and that's the
גמרא's gemara's earlier discussion before you just talk about the process of
deriving benefit you have to define if the object is the prohibited
object and at what stage does it stop being considered to be
אוכל. ochel. But let's say for
example you mixed
something foul-tasting together with it and you ate it at the same
time or something of that nature you actually by בשר בחלב basar
bechalav would still transgress even if it was not a normal way
of deriving benefit as long as the object was still considered to
be
food. So you are right, at some point the object stops being
considered food. But as long as it is you still transgress. So
אביי Abaye says the reason we were able to learn out from
כלאים kilayim to בשר בחלב basar bechalav and we didn't say כלאים
kilayim is more severe is because the exact same הלכה halacha is
true by בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. בשר בחלב basar bechalav also you
would transgress even if it was שלא כדרך הנאה. shelo k'derech hana'ah.
Then why do you need
it if you learned it from a קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? There's other reasons. You look at the גמרא gemara in
חולין Chullin because to tell you to apply to different types of
animals, other types of reasons that we learned out from the fact
that it repeats it. Okay. ואידך דקמוסיף לה. v'idach d'kamosiv lah. And
the one who challenged this, that's a good answer, בשר בחלב basar
bechalav should be the same thing. Why did he think בשר בחלב
basar bechalav should be different? It also doesn't say אכילה achilah by
בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. דקמוסיף לה. d'kamosiv lah. סבר לה הכי כגמר
מנבלה. savar lah hachi kegamar mineveilah. No no no. Because where did
we learn you can't eat בשר בחלב basar bechalav from? We learned
it from נבלה. neveilah. רש"י Rashi says technically טריפה. treifah. But it
says אנשי קודש תהיון לי ובשר בשדה טריפה לא תאכלו. anshei kodesh
tihyun li uvasar basadeh treifah lo socheilu. Remember we learned from it
in this approach that you can't eat meat and milk because of
the word קודש kodesh associated with a טריפה. treifah. So So or
טריפה *treifa*, נבלה *neveila*, etc. מה נבלה דרך הנאה derech hana'ah, אף
בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav דרך הנאה derech hana'ah. *Ma neveila derech hanaah
af basar bechalav derech hanaah*. So even though it doesn't say אכילה
achilah *achila* by בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav *basar bechalav*, it says אכילה
achilah *achila* by the נבלה *neveila* טריפה *treifa* that we learned it
from. So this approach thinks that בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav *basar bechalav*
would only be דרך derech. הנאה hana'ah, *derech hanaah*. But now we
have made a pretty strong statement and we have said that that
the act of אכילה achilah, *achila* has to be a normal type
of a process as long as the object is considered food, a,
it's maybe fit for eating, b, it's by fruit juices, certain types
of fruit juices, but as long as the object is food, you
only transgress when you eat it דרך הנאתו *derech hanaato*, the normal
way. Also things that are forbidden in הנאה hana'ah. *hanaah*, if they're
linked to the world of אכילה achilah *achila*, you also only transgress
when you get a normal type of הנאה hana'ah. *hanaah*. But things
that it doesn't use the word of אכילה *achila*, things that are
more based on the world of קודש kodesh *kodesh* or taboo or
completely off limits, like כלאים Kilayim. *kilayim* and בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav
*basar bechalav*, those you transgress even when it's שלא כדרך הנאה shelo
ke-derech hana'ah. *shelo kederech hanaah*, even when it's not in the normal
way.
And that, for example, I'll just tell you this again just as
a throw out, there's a רמ"א *Rema* discusses using the ashes that
were under, you had a fire that was cooking, that was cooked,
the Jews and non-Jews used it and sometimes they put meat pots
on it and sometimes they put milk pots on it and sometimes
the stuff would run off and it would get into the ashes
and whatever, and then you want to take these ashes and use
it for soap for washing your hair. Okay, this is a רמ"א
*Rema* in the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*. And there's a question about
being able to do this because even though it's maybe שלא כדרך
הנאה shelo ke-derech hana'ah *shelo kederech hanaah*, if it has meat particles
in it and milk particles in it and you're washing your hair
and you're getting הנאה hana'ah *hanaah*, so maybe even שלא כדרך הנאה
*shelo kederech hanaah*. Now again it raises questions: at what stage does
it stop being considered to be בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav *basar bechalav*
altogether? At what stage are you even deriving benefit from the meat
and milk? You're deriving benefit from the ashes, it just happens to
have some meat and milk taste in it, you know, maybe, but
anyway. But I just want to point out that this issue of
שלא כדרך הנאה *shelo kederech hanaah* really does is a concern in
the world of בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav. *basar bechalav*. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. ואביי
*VeAbaye*, and אביי *Abaye* would say back, how about the fact that
it's learned from נבלה *neveila* and טריפה *treifa* which says אכילה *achila*?
Okay, maybe it's learned from there, but להכי לא כתיב אכילה בגופיה
*lehachi lo ksiv achila begufei*, nevertheless the תורה Torah *Torah* doesn't say
לא תאכל *lo socheil* by בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav, *basar bechalav* itself.
It says very generic by בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav, *basar bechalav*. לומר
*Lomar*, to make the point, אפילו שלא כדרך הנאה *afilu shelo kederech
hanaah*. The emphasis there is not a formal act or process of
eating. The emphasis there by בשר בחלב Basar Bechalav *basar bechalav* is
it's off limits completely and it doesn't use the word of אכילה
*achila* to tell you that even though you can't eat and derive
benefit, it's even in a not normal way, it is completely off
limits.
It's a nice distinction, if the word הנאה *hanaah* is linked to
the word אכילה *achila*, it's bound by the same parameters for אכילה
*achila*.
Yes, that's exactly, exactly.
And if it's not linked and you learn it from a סברא
sevara *sevara* then
or not from a סברא *sevara* but also right from like the
הקדש *hekdesh* world I would say. That's exactly the point I was
making that the what we have been focusing on the last two
three days about יאכל *yocheil*, יאכלו *yeiacheilu* and then yesterday about הקדש
*hekdesh* actually presents two different models of the idea of הנאה *hanaah*.
One is a type of an extended eating like deriving benefit, bodily
pleasure like eating and therefore it's defined by a certain type of
a formal process or at least a process with some parameters as
opposed to הקדש *hekdesh* which emphasizes an object that's completely taboo and
off limits and therefore does not have those types of parameters.
So אביי *Abaye*'s answer was what? Even though we learn it from
טריפה *treifa*, it's not you don't emphasize the idea of eating since
the תורה Torah *Torah* doesn't talk about an act vis-a-vis בשר בחלב
Basar Bechalav *basar bechalav*, it talks more about just בשר בחלב Basar
Bechalav *basar bechalav* being off limits and problematic, so even when you
learn things that you can't do with it like eating and benefit,
it's not defined as a formal act.
What you learn from טריפה *treifa* is an איסור *issur* regarding this
in general, but the specifics אביי *Abaye* says you don't learn.
Exactly, exactly. Yep. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* since it
made this whole discussion about learning הנאה *hanaah* from בשר בחלב Basar
Bechalav. *basar bechalav* has to finish the conversation. So you know because
it said we can learn it from כלאים Kilayim, *kilayim* because כלאים
Kilayim *kilayim* are you did an עבירה *aveira* and it started off
and it started off being permissible, so it should be like בשר
בחלב basar be-chalav *basar bechalav* and therefore you can learn it from
כלאים Kilayim. *kilayim*. כלאים Kilayim. *kilayim* is forbidden in הנאה *hanaah*, so
is בשר בחלב *basar bechalav*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. ולפרך *Ulifroch*, one minute, why can't you learn it from כלאים
Kilayim. *kilayim*? מה כלאי הכרם שכן לא היתה לו שעת הכושר *Ma
kilayis hakerem shekein lo hayta lo shaas hakosher*. כלאי הכרם *kilayis hakerem*
also was never permissible. Meaning the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's true
the original grape seed let's say and the wheat seed were permissible
but what that's not what's כלאים Kilayim *kilayim*, what's כלאים kilayim, *kilayim*
is what grows and what grows from them was always forbidden. So
the argument is בשר בחלב *basar bechalav* has a thing that makes
it less forbidden that at least the meat originally was permissible and
the milk originally was permissible, so maybe it shouldn't be as severe,
as severe as something like ערלה orlah. *orlah* which was always forbidden.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כלאים *kilayim* was also never. Always
forbidden. As soon as it grew as כלאים it was forbidden. Anything
that grew was forbidden. So let's see the answer. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב אדא בר אהבה Amar Rav Ada bar Ahava
זו אומרת, zo omeres, the fact that it didn't challenge it that
way tells you that כלאי הכרם עיקרן נאסרו. Kilaye Hakerem ikran ne'esru.
הוי והוי להם שעת הכושר Hovei vehavei lahem sha'at hachosher that actually
the same that's true by בשר בחלב is true by כלאים. The
very root, the very seed becomes forbidden even though because but sort
of like even though it had a time that it was permitted.
If you take your grape seed and you take your wheat seed
and you plant them and out of them sprouts כלאים, even some
part again, you know, I don't know what part would remain, but
some part of that original seed would itself become forbidden as well.
So what pre-existed, the same way by בשר בחלב and actually the
comparison of כלאים and בשר בחלב is a powerful one because the
whole problem of בשר בחלב is you're mixing breeds as it were.
You know, you're taking from one world and another world and you're
crossing things. And what happens is not just the new stuff that
grows but the original stuff that was crossed also becomes forbidden. And
the גמרא Gemara says the same is true by כלאים. When you
cross two separate things and you plant them together, it's not the
new stuff that grows only that's forbidden, but even the original things
now that they've been crossed and are growing together, the original thing
becomes forbidden as well. So it actually is exactly like בשר בחלב
in that regard. Yes, you had a question, Paul.
Isn't it become forbidden retroactively? Because it's like the meat and milk
question. It's like when they say, well, at one point they were
permissible. Yeah, but once they've touched each other and were cooked together,
they weren't permissible. We're not talking about חלב, chalav, we're not talking
about בשר, we're talking about בשר בחלב. So once it becomes בשר
בחלב, it's irrelevant that they were once permissible.
Right. No, but the point is that maybe it would someone hold
on to its original status, meaning meaning maybe it doesn't become as
forbidden as something that from the very moment that it began its
life was forbidden. Since this meat was once permitted even after it's
been cooked with milk and becomes בשר בחלב, maybe it doesn't become
completely taboo because it started in a world of היתר. heter. That's
the that's at least the argument. In the end, the answer is
that it's not true. That it does become completely forbidden. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. So we're going to finish
up this discussion about כלאים. Does the actual original thing become forbidden
or just the new growth? And then we're going to move on
to another point. So let's finish up this issue of כלאים. הוי
והוי ליה שעת הכושר קודם השרשה.
Hovei vehavei lei sha'at hachosher
kodem hashrasha. Before it took root, the thing was permissible and that
thing once it takes root and they take root together, that thing
becomes the very original thing becomes forbidden as well. Okay.
כלאים produces a new plant or they're just
No, they're just growing side by side and they're right side by
side. And that's considered to be the fact that they're sort of,
you know, drawing on the nutrients from the same soil.
Exactly. It's not like בשר בחלב where it becomes something new.
True, although you could imagine a case that I've got a piece
of meat and I've got some cheese and I cook them together
and I can still see the cheese by itself and I can
still see the meat by itself, like you know like if I
make like if I make a cheeseburger, right, you know, there's some
exchange of juices so it's not exactly the same but there's still
some analogy there. It's not like they completely merge by בשר בחלב
they don't have to completely merge by בשר בחלב either. So if
I plant here a seed of a grape seed and here I
plant a, you know, wheat seed and they're next to each other
and they take root, even if there's some of the seed itself
that's still there, that seed becomes forbidden now that they have both
taken root side by side. And that's similar to the בשר בחלב.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתיב רב שמעיא. Metiv Rav
Shemaya. רב שמעיא Rav Shemaya asked: we have the following משנה. Mishna.
המעביר עציץ נקוב בכרם. Hamavir atzitz nakuv becherem. Somebody passes a flower
plant with a hole. A flower plant with a hole is considered
since the only thing that separates the dirt in the plant from
the dirt on the ground is air and there's a hole there
that so they're sort of somehow they're connected through the air. It's
considered halachically as if it's planted in the ground. So you take
this flower plant with a hole and you pass it through the
כרם, kerem, into a into a vineyard. So you basically take your
flower plant in which is growing your flower pot with a hole
I should in which is growing I don't know a stalk of
wheat and you place it down right on the floor of your
vineyard. I mean literally here you're just walking through with it, but
let's even say to make it a little more understandable that you
placed it on the ground. Okay. And then you waited a day
or two and then you took your flower pot back. אם הוסיף
מאתים, Im hosif matayim, if the let's say you had your stalk
of grain growing in this flower pot, if it grew one two-hundredth
more of its original, you know, growth, so originally there was 199
units, whatever the units are, probably volume units, 199 I don't know
whatever cubic centimeters of the grain in the flower pot and then
when you removed it from the vineyard you had 200 cubic centimeters
of grain. Wait, I'll tell you in a minute. Then אסור *assur*,
then the grain is forbidden. הוסיף *hosif*, okay, that's the הלכה *halacha*.
Now what's that based on? It's based on the הלכה *halacha* that
כלאים *kilayim* is בטל *batel* one in 200. If you have one
unit of כלאים *kilayim*, let's take a simpler case. Here I have
a piece of grain that was planted together with the vine and
it's 100 percent כלאים *kilayim*. And I mix this one stalk of
grain into 200 other stalks of grain, then it's בטל *batel*. Normal
ביטול *bitul* is one in 60, but by כלאים *kilayim* we're more
severe because it's אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah* as we just said, and
it's more than תרומה *terumah* which is one in 100, it's one
in 200. If I mix this one stalk of grain in 199
stalks, everything is forbidden, it's not enough to create to affect ביטול
*bitul*. What I have now is I have my one stalk of
grain which was 199 units of היתר *heter*. Okay, and this one
stalk of grain was in the flower pot growing in the vineyard.
And then a little bit grew more. This little bit, this one
unit more that grew, is כלאים *kilayim*. I have one unit of
כלאים *kilayim* and 199 units, the original stalk of grain, of היתר
*heter*. So that's less than one in 200. It's one against 199.
Then it's forbidden. If less than one unit grew, then it would
be enough to create ביטול *bitul*. But if one unit, one out
of 200 grew, you need one out of 201 for it to
be בטל *batel*. So if one out of 200 grew, then it's
a mixture and it's not בטל *batel*. The effect of that is
saying or the implicit point of that is, is that only the
new stuff that grew is כלאים *kilayim*. The original stalk is completely
היתר *heter*. Doesn't this go against your idea that once they're growing
together, the original thing becomes כלאים *kilayim*? Here you see that it's
only what grew that became
כלאים *kilayim*. הוסיף אין *hosif in*, only if it got added, yes,
לא הוסיף לא *lo hosif lo*, if nothing got
added if enough was not added new, it's not a problem. Why
don't we just say the fact that it was growing in the
vineyard made the original stalk כלאים *kilayim*? So that's a pretty good
proof that the original thing does not become forbidden. So אמר רב
דקא ואמר רבי Rebbi *amar Rav Daka ve-amar Rabbi*, I'm sorry, skipped
a lot. לא הוסיף לא *lo hosif lo*. אמר רבא Rava. תרי
קראי כתיבי *amar Rava terei krai ksivi*. You're right, there are two
different פסוקים *psukim* and two different ways in which something becomes
כלאים *kilayim*. כתיב *ksiv*, one verse says הזרע *hazera*, פן תקדש המלאה
הזרע
אשר תזרע *pen
tikdash hamlei'ah hazera asher tizra*. Okay, so it's actually the same פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. כתיב הזרע וכתיב המלאה *ksiv hazera u-ksiv hamlei'ah*. The seed
and the מלאה *mlei'ah*, the full, meaning the growth. So the פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* both talks about what becomes forbidden.
One refers to the original seed and one refers to the fullness,
the growth. הכיצד *hakeitzad*, so which is it? Does the original seed
become forbidden or does the growth become forbidden? So זרוע מעיקרו *zaru'a
mei'ikaro*, something was already planted, like this case about the you didn't
plant the two seeds together. You took the flower pot that had
in it the growing stalk of wheat. So the stalk of wheat
was already planted. In that case, זרוע מעיקרו *zaru'a mei'ikaro* בהשרשה *behashrasha*.
זרוע ובא
*zaru'a uva*, I'm sorry, I read that wrong. זרוע מעיקרו *zaru'a mei'ikaro*,
if you planted them originally together, you originally planted the grape seed
and the wheat seed together, then בהשרשה *behashrasha*, then as soon as
it takes root the very זרע *zera*, the very origin of it
becomes forbidden. זרוע ובא *zaru'a uva*, if it was already planted, like
you took the flower pot with the wheat into the vineyard, in
that case הוסיף אין לא הוסיף לא *hosif in lo hosif lo*.
It's only the stuff that grows, it's only the מלאה *mlei'ah*, it's
not the original. So we actually say there's two forms of כלאים
*kilayim*. When you plant the כלאים *kilayim* together, it's actually you can
even understand the model, right, because it's like doing the act of
cooking בשר בחלב *basar bechalav*. When you plant, the תורה Torah *Torah*
emphasizes לא תזרע כרמך כלאים *lo tizra karmecha kilayim*. Don't plant them
together. So when you plant them together, the very things that you
planted themselves become forbidden even if the original thing become forbidden, not
only the growth. If, however, something wasn't planted together, it was planted
separately but it just grew together, you move the flower pot, then
it's only the new stuff that grows, but it's not the original,
that stuff does not become כלאים *kilayim*. If you don't plant at
the same time. Right, so logically then the question would be, what
if I actually
put a wheat seed in a vineyard? So the seeds weren't planted
together, half of it was זרוע מעיקרו *zaru'a mei'ikaro*, not the other
half. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s unclear about that. That's a good
question. Right, we have the two extremes. Planting the two seeds together,
or both were originally planted,
the wheat stalk was originally planted and the vineyard was originally planted
and then you bring them together. What's if you have one planted,
the growing vineyard and you throw wheat seeds into it? That would
be a good question. Okay, but that at least is what רבא
Rava says that you have these two models. Okay. So that ends
our discussion of דרך הנאה, which really gets to the root of
how you conceptualize the act of benefit. Is it a derivative type
of אכילה rooted in the world of אכילה and therefore has to
be a normal way of deriving benefit, or is it completely based
on being קודש off limits forbidden, like things like בשר בחלב and
כלאים, which is even לא כדרך הנאה. lo k-derech hana'ah.
Now we that we're talking about הנאה, we get to another statement
which evokes much larger discussions in the in other גמרות. gemarot. Let's
take a look.
אמר רבי יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yakov Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
says Rabbi Yakov in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, בכל מתרפאין חוץ
מעצי אשרה. bekhol mitrappin chutz me-atzei Asherah. You can heal yourself with
all types of things, meaning even things that are forbidden in benefit,
with the exception of אשרה Asherah wood, wood that has been worshipped
as עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Now you're not worshipping the wood, you're just using it to heal
you from a certain type of a tree, but you cannot use
that. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the case? אי נימא דאיכא סכנה, iy neima d'ika sakanah, if
there's a risk of life, then אפילו עצי אשרה נמי לא, afilu
atzei Asherah nami lo, then you can't then אפילו עצי אשרה נמי,
afilu atzei Asherah nami, you should even be able to use אשרה
Asherah wood. I mean, you know, it's a risk of life, you're
not worshipping עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you're just using the wood of
the tree. ואי ליכא סכנה, ve-iy leika sakanah, if there's no risk
of life, then אפילו כל איסורים שבתורה נמי לא, afilu kol issurim
she-ba-Torah nami lo, then even other things that are forbidden you shouldn't
be able to use because it's still biblically prohibited to derive benefit
if there are things that you can't derive benefit from or maybe
you want to eat them to for health, and you shouldn't be
allowed to do that if there's not a real risk to life.
So what's the case? What's the case? What other things you can
use but you can't use אשרה Asherah wood? So the גמרא Gemara
says לעולם דאיכא סכנה, le-olam d'ika sakanah, we're talking that there is
a risk to life, ואפילו הכי עצי אשרה לא. ve-afilu hakhi atzei
Asherah lo. And even though there's a risk of life, you cannot
use and therefore you can transgress any prohibition for risk of life,
the one thing you can't do though is you can't use אשרה
Asherah wood. Why can't you use אשרה Asherah wood? דתניא, de-tanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, said
Rabbi Eliezer, אם נאמר בכל נפשך, im ne-emar bekhol nafshekha, if the
Torah says love God with all your soul, למה נאמר בכל מאדך?
lamah ne-emar bekhol me'odekha? Why does it say all your might? ואם
נאמר בכל מאדך למה נאמר בכל נפשך? ve-im ne-emar bekhol me'odekha lamah
ne-emar bekhol nafshekha? And if it says all your might, why does
it say all your soul? אלא לומר לך, ella lomar lekha, to
tell you, אם יש אדם שגופו חביב עליו מממונו, im yesh adam
she-gufo chaviv alav mi-mamono, if there's somebody whose body is more dear
to him than his property,
לכך נאמר בכל נפשך, le-khakh ne-emar bekhol nafshekha, then you have to
be prepared to give up your your body, your soul, your very
life for God. ויש אדם שממונו חביב עליו מגופו, ve-yesh adam she-mamono
chaviv alav mi-gufo, and if there's somebody whose money is more dear
than their property, לכך נאמר בכל מאדך, le-khakh ne-emar bekhol me'odekha, therefore
it says with all of your wealth. It's like I'm going to
really date myself here, but it's like the famous Jack Benny line,
you know the Jack Benny line? He says guy comes up to
him in the street, says your money or your life? He says
I'm deciding, I'm deciding, I'm thinking. So anyway,
he's quiet, he's quiet, yes that's right, he says I'm thinking, I'm
thinking.
So anyway, but the point of that here is to say that
is to say that the פסוק does not just mean like like
metaphorically love God with all your strength, it really means you have
to be prepared to sacrifice, sacrifice your money, sacrifice your life. And
therefore from there we learn that you have to sometimes martyr yourself
because of the מצווה mitzvah of אהבת השם, ahavat Hashem, which is
where which the גמרא Gemara, understands me... so let's take a look
at the next line. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata
Ravin Amar Rabbi Yochanan, בכל מתרפאין, bekhol mitrappin, and I'll just read
this next line then go back to discuss the point before. So,
but that teaches you you can basically... so in a similar way
Ravin said in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, you can use anything
to heal yourself with, חוץ מעבודה זרה וגלוי עריות ושפיכות דמים. chutz
me-avodah zarah ve-gillui arayot ve-shfikhut damim. And now we see the context
we're putting it in. Meaning the same three things you have to
martyr yourself for rather than do, idol worship, forbidden sexual relations, and
murder, those three things you have to be prepared to give up
your life. So if you have to be prepared to give up
your life rather than do them if somebody's holding a gun to
your head, similarly, you have to be prepared to give up your
life rather than do them if doing them will somehow save you
from some sickness or from some disease. You know, so they ask
this famous question on this like ethics sort of test about, you
know, your son is deathly sick and the, you know, and the
pharmacist has, you know, the medication costs $5,000 and you don't have
any money, you know, and what do you do? Do you see,
you know, does that allow you to steal in order to, you
know, to save your to save your son's life? So, so we
won't discuss that question, but certainly if somebody's standing between you and
that and you'd have to kill the person in order to get
the medicine, that you're not allowed to do. The same three things
you can't do if somebody's holding a gun to your head, you
can't do if you need to do them in order because to
save yourself from some type of illness or sickness or danger in
life. Now, that's why we quoted loving God with all of your
soul, 'cause that is where we learn that you have to give
up your life rather
than... Now, how about using the אשרה Asherah tree? You're not doing
an act of עבודה זרה; Avodah Zarah; you're transgressing a biblical prohibition
of deriving benefit from עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you're not doing
an act of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So תוספות Tosafot says you're
right. And really it would be okay if somebody said, you know,
we need bark or we need apples, and the only apples or
the bark of the apple tree that was available happened to be
an אשרה Asherah that was worshiped in the city and that was
the only place you could find an apple. It's like, okay, you
transgress a prohibition of deriving benefit from עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but
that you're allowed to do. The thing you can't do says תוספות
Tosafot is if somebody says that oh, this אשרה Asherah tree will
help you because it has very special powers because, and that's why
everybody in the town worships it is because of the powers of
this tree. And it's not because it happens, happens to be an
אשרה Asherah tree, it's the benefit is because of the belief in
its powers. And תוספות Tosafot says, yes, it says שדים shedim and
other things, but the point is because that's because of it's worshiped
because of this, and that's the power that will heal you. That
תוספות Tosafot says that already is something that's a gateway to real
belief in the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and therefore that's where you
have to give up your life. So that's תוספות's Tosafot approach. Other
ראשונים Rishonim disagree. The ר"ן Ran says, he says, no, even if
technically it's not עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and it's not going to
lead to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, any prohibition that comes from the
world of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg v'al
ya'avor, even if it is not something that actually leads to actual
idol worship itself. And that is called אביזריהו דעבודה זרה, avizrayhu d'Avodah
Zarah, even the appurtenances. You know, even the things that are somehow
connected to that world even if they're not the thing itself. And
this is a very important debate of ראשונים Rishonim and comes up
in a number of ways because it gets to issues like אביזריהו
דגילוי עריות. avizrayhu d'gilluy arayot. You know, you'll hear people saying things
and sometimes it sounds like hyperbole and sometimes they mean it, like
you know, you know, it's יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor to
go mixed swimming. Why? Because אביזריהו דגילוי עריות. avizrayhu d'gilluy arayot. It's
actually, it's not actual forbidden sex, but it's a prohibition within the
constellation of that. And anything that's within that constellation is יהרג ואל
יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor the same way the thing itself is
יהרג
ואל יעבור.
yehareg
v'al ya'avor. Okay. Right. נגיעה? negi'ah? יהרג ואל יעבור. yehareg v'al ya'avor.
Exactly. Exactly. So תוספות Tosafot disagrees with this. Actually, this question came
up to the רא"ש. Rosh. The רא"ש Rosh was asked, it's very
sad reality, but we know this was true that during the Crusades,
of maybe very appropriate for תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. During the Crusades
sometimes the Jews would run into the churches because sometimes it would
be the rabble that was sort of, you know, sometimes they were
led by priests but sometimes not, you know, in their killing of
Jews. And the Jews, sometimes the priests would protect them and there
were cases the Jews would run into these, you know, fortified churches
to protect themselves against the rabble. And the question was asked to
the רא"ש, Rosh, can we do that? Or is that saving yourself
with עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? With, you know, because in the Middle
Ages, whatever, Christianity, I mean even now, whatever, we won't have this
whole discussion, but anyway, it was working with the assumption that it
had the same status as classic עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And the
רא"ש Rosh basically said you're protecting yourself not because of the salvific
powers of the church, but because of the walls of the church.
So therefore it's allowed. So anyway, this was the question. Is the
prohibition, is the fact that you can't use these things only real
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah or things that lead to עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah because you believe in the salvific powers of it, or is
it any prohibition that's somewhere in the penumbra, somewhere in the constellation
of these things is equal יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor to
the thing itself? Major, major debate based on the ambiguity of this
גמרא.
Gemara What does the רמב"ם Rambam say? רמב"ם Rambam says עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah as long as you don't believe that the power supersedes
the power of הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, I think it's
not עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah if I remember correctly.
Well, the רמב"ם Rambam also very clearly says that Christianity is עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, so anyway, yeah, so that's many, many times.
Yeah, exactly. I don't want to get into right, that, exactly what,
what beliefs constitute that.
But yeah, this whole description sounds a little like what was it?
נעמן, Naaman, who אלישע Elisha cured with the waters of the Jordan?
Right. Oh right, got other rivers. No, no, you want this one.
Right, right, right. That's a very good comparison, right. להבדיל. lehavdil. Right,
exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, so now turning the
page, the גמרא Gemara says these three things, עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
גילוי עריות, ושפיכות דמים. gilluy arayot v'shifichut damim, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
הא דאמרן, ha d'amran, עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah we've seen, love God
with all your life, so that's considered, you know, denying your love
and fidelity to God, you have to be willing to give up
your life rather than do it. גילוי עריות gilluy arayot, ושפיכות דמים,
v'shifichut damim. how about the other big two? How about forbidden sexual
acts and murder? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught a ברייתא, braita, רבי אומר,
omer, כי כאשר יקום איש על רעהו ורצחו נפש כן הדבר הזה.
ki ka'asher yakum ish al re'ehu u'retzacho nefesh ken hadavar hazeh. So
the תורה's talking here about a woman who was raped, and it
says
the woman is guiltless, she was raped. She called out, nobody saved
her, she couldn't do anything about it, and it's just like a
murder victim. The same way you don't blame a murder victim, you
should not blame the victim of rape, which obviously seems self-evident, of
course very sadly that's not true in so many ancient societies and
even today, you know, there are many societies in which a woman
who is the victim of rape is the one who is blamed
and not the actual person who commits it, right, honor killing and
so on. So the תורה says no, she's like a murder victim,
she has no fault. וכי vechi so now the גמרא Gemara says,
so that's a very clear פסוק, but the גמרא Gemara asks, וכי
מה עניין רוצח אצל נערה המאורסה? vechi mah inyan rotzeach etzel na'arah
hame'orasah? What's the point of comparing a murder to a
rapist? הרי זה בא ללמד ונמצא למד. harei zeh ba lelamed venimtza
lamed. It's coming to teach you something, that this woman was faultless,
but you also wind up learning something. What do you learn from
it? מקיש רוצח לנערה המאורסה. makish rotzeach lena'arah hame'orasah. You link the
case of the murder to a case of a woman who was
raped, this married woman. מה נערה המאורסה, mah na'arah hame'orasah, what's the
case about this married maiden? ניתנה להצילה בנפשו. nitnah lehatzilah benafsho. You
know that you are allowed to kill the rapist, the attempted rapist
to protect the woman. How do you know you're allowed to do
that? Because it says, she called out, צעקה הנערה המאורסה, tza'akah hana'arah
hame'orasah, she called out, ואין מושיע לה, ve'ein moshia lah, nobody came
to save her. So therefore the implication being that if you were
able to save her, you would have actually been allowed or had
a mandate to save her. So we learn from נערה המאורסה na'arah
hame'orasah that you are allowed to intervene to protect or mandated to
intervene to protect even at the cost of the life of the
rapist or of the attempted rapist.
So, מה נערה המאורסה ניתנה להצילה בנפשו, mah na'arah hame'orasah nitnah lehatzilah
benafsho, you can save her, notice the difference of the gender here,
להצילה, lehatzilah, you can save her, בנפשו, benafsho, in his life, by
through the life of the attempted rapist. אף רוצח, af rotzeach, even
in the case of a murderer, an attempted murderer, ניתן להצילו בנפשו,
nitan lehatzilo benafsho, you can save the victim with the life of
the attempted murderer. So one thing you learn out is your mandate,
your permission and I would say your mandate to intervene to protect.
That's one thing you learn out. ונערה המאורסה מרצח. vena'arah hame'orasah merotzeach.
Now you also learn a law about נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah from
the case of murder. What do you learn there? מה רוצח יהרג
ואל יעבור, mah rotzeach yehareg ve'al ya'avor, the same way by murder
you should be killed rather than to transgress, אף נערה המאורסה, af
na'arah hame'orasah, similarly by a case of a woman who is being
you know who is being raped but here the point would be
being forced in a forbidden sexual act, תיהרג ואל תעבור, tehareg ve'al
ta'avor, she should rather be killed than transgress. Okay, so the same
way they're similar and the same way you don't transgress to commit
murder, you let yourself be killed, the same way should be true
about forbidden sexual acts. Now, let me just finish this thought and
then I'll go back to that. ושפיכות דמים גופיה מנלן? ushfikhut damim
gufeih minalan? And how do you know about murder? How maybe you
should commit murder to save your own life? How do you know
you don't? סברא הוא, sevara hu, it's logic. כי הא דההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבא, ki ha de'ahu de'ata lekamei deRava, like there was the
man that came in front of רבא. אמר ליה amar leih and
he said to him, מרי דוראי, marei dorai, the master of my
city, אמר לי, amar li, has said to me, זיל קטליה לפלניא,
zil katleih lefalanya, go kill so-and-so, ואי לא קטלינא לך, ve'i lo
katlina lakh, and if you don't kill this person, I'll kill you.
So what should I do? Should I kill him or should I
let myself be killed? So a classic case about יהרג ואל יעבור.
yehareg ve'al ya'avor. אמר ליה, amar leih, so רבא said to him,
ליקטלוך, likatlukha, let him kill you, ולא תיקטול, velo tiktol, and you
should not kill this other person. Why? מאי חזית דדמא דידך סומק
טפי? mai chazit dedama didakh sumak tfi? What makes you think your
blood is the redder blood? דילמא דמא דהוא גברא סומק טפי? dilma
dama de'ahu gavra sumak tfi? Maybe this guy's blood is redder than
yours? So what lets gives you the right to sacrifice somebody else's
life for your life? Basically you're choosing that your life is more
important than his. What allows you to do that? And רש"י Rashi
emphasizes you are
what allows you to commit the crime of murder, to commit the
sin of murder
by making that choice. Maybe, you know, the question is if somebody
else was like if somebody said, "Who should I kill, you or
him?" You know, maybe then you're allowed to say, "I'd rather you
kill the other guy than me." You're not at least the one
you're maybe you're not saying in some objective reality my blood is
redder, but maybe I'm entitled, you know, there's this other principle of
חייך וחיי אחיך, chayecha vechayei achicha, you're entitled to protect your life
over somebody else's, right? But that's when you're not committing a sin.
There's no license to commit the sin of murder for the virtue
of saving your life. Why why does that give you license to
commit that sin if you're basically taking another life in the process?
So from this we learn out from this סברא we learn out
that you cannot save another life you know commit the sin of
murder in order to protect your life and therefore since that's true
about murder and murder is compared to this case about נערה המאורסה
na'arah hame'orasah about this woman which is a case of forbidden sexual
acts, similarly you cannot commit a forbidden sexual act for the purpose
of saving of saving your life. Now, there are some interesting questions
about this, a lot of interesting questions which we're not going to
solve now. Given that we have what? Five minutes left, so I'll
just raise them very quickly. Number one, the issue about the case
about the woman and the rapist is a big discussion in the
ראשונים Rishonim based on another גמרא, Gemara whether the גרסא girsa here,
here's where grammar makes such a difference, whether the גרסא girsa by
the woman is תהרג ואל תעבור, teihareig ve'al ta'avor, she should let
herself be killed, or יהרג, yeihareig, you, if a man is being
told to commit a forbidden sexual act, should let himself be killed.
The difference being that the גמרא Gemara in some place says that
by אסתר Esther in particular where it talks about her
being willing to commit this sin of sleeping with אחשורוש Achashveirosh in
order to save the Jewish people, the idea of קרקע עולם, karka
olam, is passive, and does being passive make it more allowed? Now
what exactly does the גמרא Gemara mean by passive? I mean, does
it really imagine that in the act of sex the woman is
completely passive? So the רמב"ן Ramban actually makes an excellent point specifically
in the context of rape. The רמב"ן Ramban says in rape, even
if a woman wanted to give up her life rather than to
commit it, she could be forced to have sex, even if she
wanted to choose to give up her life, the act could still
be forced upon her. So
therefore she's not really in control of whether to say take my
life or do the act or whatnot and therefore she could be
considered to be, it might be different in that case where she
doesn't have to give up her life because maybe even being willing
to give up her life wouldn't make a difference. That's the one
issue by the case about the woman. The other important question about
the forbidden sexual act is what's included in that? The גמרא here
speaks specifically about an issue of rape, which is really an act
of violence against a person. And you could imagine other forms of
forbidden sexual acts
which are similar, even if it were something
like committing adultery, there's other people involved to whom that act, even
if the parties are willing,
but the people they're married to that it's sort of still an
act against another person. But what about certain acts of forbidden sex
to which there's no victims as it were? Let's say it was
a case about a prohibition of נדה, niddah, right? Would that be
יהרג ואל יעבור yeihareig ve'al ya'avor by נדה niddah as well? What
constitutes גילוי עריות gilluy arayot here that's learned from this world of
the rape of a married woman? What would be included in that
is also not fully clear. The general assumption in the ראשונים Rishonim
is anything that's called an עריות. arayot. But at least it's worth
noting that problem. The other thing I will say about the case
about the שפיכות דמים shefichut damim that's also open-ended is let's say
there is a case of דמא דידך סומק טפי. dema didach sumach
tfei. Let's say there's a case where if I kill this one
person I'll save ten lives. Do you make that type of a
math or do you say when it comes to life every life
is infinite and you're not allowed to ever make that math and
actively make this type of a choice? It's sort of like that
Sophie's Choice, right? Sophie's Choice. So anyway, these are very powerful questions
about the exact parameters of this which I just sort of leave
us to ponder rather than to give you answers.
The תלמוד Talmud assumes all this is between Jews?
Yes, and that's also true.
Right, רש"י Rashi in particular emphasizes Jews although that's not explicit in
the גמרא but רש"י Rashi certainly does emphasize it. נפש ישראל אבודה,
Nefesh Yisrael avudah, רש"י Rashi says.
Yes, I also want to point out that it's not the rape
itself that's
the core violence, it's the fact that she belonged to another
man, it's an
act of damaging someone else's property. Because if she's not מאורסה me'orasah
and she's not married then it's not a crime at all.
Well, it's still, I mean there's still consequences to it. Right, so
there's the חזון איש Chazon Ish that actually asks that point. You're
right, but the גמרא's assumption for example if a woman is about
to be raped and she's an unmarried woman can you kill the
attempted rapist to protect her? So the חזון איש Chazon Ish raises
this issue, but I don't remember, if she's not
מאורסה. me'orasah.
Right, well the case in the תורה that the גמרא's emphasizing is
exactly the מאורסה me'orasah and you're absolutely right. The גמרא's not emphasizing
the violence of the rape but the forbidden act of sex which
would be presumably even with willing parties and that's
exactly taking it from a case which is much more sort of
intuitively understandable to us because of the violent nature, the גמרא's implicitly
bracketing that. Let's just read one more section here and then we
will end. I know we're a little over but we're about to
take a day break for תשעה באב Tisha B'Av so if people
have to go they can go but I just want to read
the next case. ההוא גברא, Ahu gavra, I'm sorry, מר בר רב
אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi אשכחיה ashchei one more case here about
things about deriving benefit. מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
אשכחיה ashchei לרבינא leRavina דשייפיה לברתיה בגוהרקא דערלה. deshaifleh leberteih beguharki de'orlah.
He was sort of rubbing his daughter with the peels of ערלה.
orlah daughter with the leaves with some type of a juice from
unripe, let's say olives or something, or maybe olive juice that had
in it all of the sediment and he was rubbing this on
his daughter. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so he said to him, and
presumably for a health purpose. So he said to him, אימא דאמרי
רבנן Eima de-amri rabbanan בשעת סכנה, be-sha'at sakanah, when did the Rabbis
say? Now ערלה orlah you remember is forbidden in הנאה. Now he
said to him,
and ערלה orlah though it does say אכילה, so it's only normal
הנאה. But he says, wait a minute, he says, when did the
Rabbis say you're allowed to use these when there's a risk of
life? You can derive benefit from things that are forbidden. שלא בשעת
סכנה מי אמר, Shelo be-sha'at sakanah mi amar, who said you could
do it when there's not a risk of life? אמר ליה, Amar
leh, he said back to him, האי אישתא צמירתא נמי כשעת סכנה
דמיא. Hai ishta tzamirta nami ke-sha'at sakanah damya. This high fever is
like a risk of life. I really think that this is a
potential risk of life and therefore that's why I'm doing it. Okay,
so that's one answer which basically just says that certain, you know,
high fevers are within the category of סכנה. sakanah. איכא דאמרי, Ika
de-amri, now there's another answer which is he said to him, אמר
ליה, Amar leh, מידי דרך הנאה קא עבידנא? Midi derech hana'ah ka
avidna? What, do you think I'm doing it in the normal way
of benefit? This is just like unripe olives, it's olives with sediment
in it, it's not דרך. And this is a closure to the
previous discussion that things that it says אכילה like ערלה are only
forbidden when it's דרך הנאה. To use it in this state, to
use it in this unripe state, or to use it with the
sediment is not the normal way and therefore it is actually not
a biblical transgression. Now, the ראשונים Rishonim point out that doesn't mean
it's מותר. mutar. That means that it's still rabbinically forbidden. But to
do it for a health purpose, to do it for a רפואה
refuah purpose, that would be permissible to do שלא כדרך הנאה. So
this is nice closure to what we opened with that שלא כדרך
הנאה is not, you don't get lashes for. Here we're finding out
you don't get lashes, it's still forbidden, but it was permissible to
do for the sake of רפואה, refuah, for the sake of health
purposes. And we will continue with this whole discussion of הנאה come
Wednesday.